Guide to the James E. Jackson and Esther Cooper Jackson Papers TAM 347
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
James E. Jackson and Esther Cooper Jackson Papers
Bulk, 1937-1992
1917-2008, (Bulk 1937-1992)
TAM 347
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
22.25 linear feet (23 boxes)
James E. Jackson (1914-2007) and Esther Cooper Jackson (1917- ) are African American communists and civil rights activists, best known for their role in founding and leading the Southern Negro Youth Congress (1937-48). James Jackson was head of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) Louisiana state organization in 1946, and was a Party organizer in the automobile industry in Detroit from 1947-50. He then moved to New York, becoming the Southern Director for the Communist Party. In 1951 he was indicted under the Smith Act (charged with advocating the overthrow of the government), and became a fugitive until 1955. He later served as the Communist Party's Educational Director and as International Affairs Secretary, retiring in 1991. Esther Cooper Jackson served as Executive Secretary of the Southern Negro Congress from 1942-1946 and co-founded and served as the managing editor from 1961-86 of Freedomways, the influential African American political and cultural quarterly. The papers contain clippings (articles by and about Jackson), correspondence of both Esther Cooper and James E. Jackson, including the Jacksons' voluminous World War II correspondence with each other, James Jackson's lectures (typescripts and audiocassettes), research notebooks, speeches, and writings (published and unpublished), subject files, correspondence, internal documents and printed ephemera pertaining to the Southern Negro Youth Congress, and to Freedomways, legal and other materials pertaining to the Smith Act indictments of James Jackson and other communists, Communist Party internal documents, many of a programmatic nature, and memorabilia and other biographical materials. Individuals represented in the collection include: Carl Bloice, Lloyd Brown, Dorothy and Louis Burnham, Angela Davis, Benjamin Davis, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Eugene and Peggy Dennis, Shirley Graham Du Bois, W.E.B. Du Bois, Martin Duberman, Viriginia Durr, William Z. Foster, Simon Gerson, Gus Hall, Ollie Harrington, Hosea Hudson, Alphaeus Hunton, Pablo Neruda, John Pittman, Pete Seeger, Edward Strong, Alice Walker, Mary Helen Washington, Jim West, Robert Williams, Henry Winston, and Carl Winter. This collection is temporarily closed to researchers.
Jackson, James E., 1914-2007
Box 1-28
Provenance
Gift of James and Esther Jackson, 2005-2006.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. This collection is temporarily closed to researchers.
Historical/Biographical Note
James E. Jackson (1914-2007) and Esther Cooper Jackson (1917- ) are African American communists and civil rights activists, best known for their role in founding and leading the Southern Negro Youth Congress (1937-1948). Both were raised in middle-class families with histories of civil rights activism. James Jackson senior was a druggist in Richmond, Virginia. Raised in Arlington, Virginia, Esther Cooper's father was a lieutenant in the U.S. army, and her mother worked in the U.S. Forestry Service during World War I and later became actively involved in the Arlington, Virginia chapter of the NAACP and in local school desegregation campaigns. James Jackson graduated from Virginia Union University in 1934, and at Howard University (the alma mater of his parents) graduated from the College of Pharmacy in 1937. After attending Dunbar High School in Washington D.C., Esther Cooper graduated from Oberlin College in 1938, then completed her master's degree at Fisk University in 1940, writing as her thesis Negro Women Domestic Workers in Relation to Trade Unionism. James Jackson joined the Communist Party in 1931, and Esther Cooper joined in 1939. The couple met in 1939 (they married in 1941) when Jackson was staying at Fisk while working for Ralph Bunche as an investigator for what would become Gunnar Myrdal's An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy(1944).
The Southern Negro Youth Congress, a communist-led popular front organization, conceived at the first National Negro Congress in 1936, held its first annual conference, organized by James Jackson and Ed Strong, in Richmond, in February, 1937. Jackson and Cooper played leading roles throughout the SNYC's first decade, as indicated by its letterhead from 1946, where Cooper is the Executive Secretary, Jackson the Special Projects Director, and their fellow-communists and close friends Louis and Dorothy Burnham were, respectively, Organizational Secretary and Educational Director. In 1938 Jackson helped lead the successful organizing of the United Tobacco Stemmers and Laborers Union Local 279 in Richmond. In 1939 the SNYC moved is headquarters to Birmingham, Alabama, with its large concentration of African American industrial workers. Under is slogan "Freedom, Equality, Opportunity," the SNYC campaigned for the full range civil, economic, political, and social rights for African Americans. Activities and issues included, in addition to supporting labor organizing (including domestic workers), campaigns against lynching, police brutality and the poll tax, for the right to vote and an end to segregation, for an end to employment discrimination (sometimes via consumer boycotts), and during World War II, for enforcement of the U.S. Fair Employment Practices Committee's resolution 8802 barring discrimination in war industries. The SNYC also published the periodical Cavalcade: The March of Southern Youth, and supported educational and cultural activities, including "People's Theaters." The SNYC held its last conference in 1948, and the pressure of Cold War anti-communism led to its subsequent dissolution. However, SNYC members went on to play important roles in the civil rights movement of the 19650s-60s, including E.D. Nixon, and several became elected officials.
Jackson entered the army in 1943 and served in the Burma theatre for some eighteen months, attainting the rank of sergeant, and during which time he and Esther corresponded daily. In the fall of 1945, Esther attended the World Youth Congress in London, where she met W.E.B. Du Bois, beginning a close association with the Jacksons culminating in his decision to join the Communist Party in 1961. In 1946 Jackson became State Chairman of the Communist Party of Louisiana. In 1947 the Jacksons moved to Detroit, where they shared a house with future Detroit mayor Coleman Young, and where James Jackson began work as a Party organizer among the autoworkers, while Esther Cooper Jackson was active in the local branches of the Progressive Party and of the Civil Rights Congress, another popular front organization. In 1951 the Jacksons moved to New York and James was named Southern Director of the Communist Party. Later that year he was indicted under the Smith Act (charged with advocating the overthrow of the U.S. government) and went underground to avoid arrest, while Esther Cooper Jackson worked for the National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership and the Families of Smith Act Victims. Emerging five years later, Jackson was sentenced to prison, although he did not serve time as the Smith Act was declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court.
Thereafter, James Jackson served as a full-time Party official, including as a member of its leading Political Bureau, and as Education Director and as International Affairs Secretary, in which capacity he traveled throughout the Communist countries and elsewhere. Meanwhile, Esther Cooper Jackson helped found in 1961 the influential African American political and cultural quarterly, Freedomways, and served as its editor throughout its publication, from 1961 to 1986. James Jackson retired in 1991, in the aftermath of the 1991 split in the CPUSA.
Sources:
Jackson, Esther Cooper. This Is My Husband: Fighter for His People, Political Refugee. (New York: National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership, 1953).
Kelley, Robin D.G. 'Southern Negro Youth Congress.' In Encyclopedia of the American Left, pp. 737-9. (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1992).
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain clippings (articles by and about Jackson), correspondence of both Esther and James Jackson, including the Jacksons' voluminous World War II correspondence with each other, James Jackson's lectures (typescripts and audiocassettes), research notebooks, speeches, and writings (published and unpublished), subject files, correspondence, internal documents and printed ephemera pertaining to the Southern Negro Youth Congress, and to Freedomways, legal and other materials pertaining to the Smith Act indictments of Jackson and other communists, Communist Party internal documents, many of a programmatic nature, and memorabilia and other biographical materials. Individuals represented in the collection include: Carl Bloice, Lloyd Brown, Dorothy and Louis Burnham, Angela Davis, Benjamin Davis, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Eugene and Peggy Dennis, Shirley Graham Du Bois, W.E.B. Du Bois, Martin Duberman, Viriginia Durr, William Z. Foster, Simon Gerson, Gus Hall, Ollie Harrington, Hosea Hudson, Alphaeus Hunton, Pablo Neruda, John Pittman, Pete Seeger, Edward Strong, Alice Walker, Mary Helen Washington, Jim West, Robert Williams, Henry Winston, and Carl Winter.
Series I. Biographical and Memorabilia, contains some genealogical and family history materials, including interview transcripts, documents relating to Jackson's army service, and honorary and identification documents.
Series II. Clippings, contains clippings by and about James Jackson, most from the 1960s-80s.
Series III. Communist Party USA contains internal documents relating to conventions, Party programs, African Americans, the Party crisis of 1989-91, and other topics.
Series IV. Correspondence contains James Jackson's correspondence, and some third party correspondence, and is divided into three subseries: alphabetical, chronological, and third party correspondence. Notable names include Carl Bloice ( Daily World), Benjamin Davis, Eugene and Peggy Dennis, W.E.B. Du Bois, Simon Gerson, Gus Hall, Ollie Harrington, Hosea Hudson, Pablo Neruda, John Pittman, Ed Strong, Henry Winston, and Carl Winter.
Series V. Correspondence, Army contains the almost daily letters exchanged between James and Esther in 1944-5 (and some earlier letters from 1943), correspondence with James E. Jackson Sr., and letters from Louis and Dorothy Burnham.
Series VI. Freedomways(Esther Cooper Jackson) contains editorial correspondence, files on a special issue devoted to Paul Robeson and the publication of Paul Robeson: The Great Forerunner, files on a centennial tribute to W.E.B. Du Bois, and files on financial issues. Notable correspondents include: John Conyers, Ruby Dee, Ralph Ellison, Shirley Graham Du Bois, Paul Robeson Jr., and Coleman Young.
Series VII. Esther Cooper Jackson Papers, contains her correspondence with African American progressives and correspondence with historians and other researchers, including Robeson biographer Martin Duberman, and writings, including her M.A. thesis Negro Women Domestic Workers in Relation to Trade Unionism. Notable correspondents include: Lloyd Brown, Dorothy and Margaret Ann Burnham, Ossie Davis and Ruby Dee, Virginia Durr, Shirley Graham Du Bois, Pete Seeger, and Alice Walker.
Series VIII. Lectures, contains Jackson's typescripts for educational lectures delivered in Communist Party fora. Topics include Africa and African Americans, dialectical and historical materialism, Marxism-Leninism, Party history and organization, and political economy.
Series IX. Notebooks, contains 86 research and reading notebooks, most undated and untitled, but almost all post-1960. Three notebooks discuss Vietnam.
Series X. Smith Act contains briefs, testimony and other legal documents relating to Jackson's indictment and trial, materials of the James Jackson Defense Committee, and clippings and correspondence.
Series XI. Southern Negro Youth Congress, contains correspondence of SNYC officials, letters from E.D. Nixon and Thurgood Marshall, circulars, constitutions, leaflets, flyers, a manual or organization, pamphlets, programs, reports, several issues of Cavalcade, "The Southern Hate Press: A Threat to Post-War Democracy" by Esther Cooper, later correspondence with academics, FBI FOIA files requested by Robin Kelley, and an interview with James Jackson.
Series XII. Speeches, contains texts of Jackson's speeches on a variety of topics given from 1946 to 2001.
Series XIII. Subject Files contains a variety of published and unpublished documents, and is arranged alphabetically by event, title, or topic. About half the materials relate to African American politics and social conditions, with the remainder relating to a broad range of domestic and international affairs, and the international communist movement. Notable files include American Dilemma Study Material, a Detroit Red Squad FOIA file, and five folders of photocopies of Ollie Harrington drawings and cartoons (the originals have been separated to the Library's non-print collection).
Series XIV. Writings, Published is divided into three subseries: Articles, Leaflets, and Pamphlets, The most frequent topics in this wide-ranging series are African American politics and social conditions, international communism and politics, and appreciations of or memorials for notable communists and progressives.
Series XV. Writings, Unpublished are arranged alphabetically and cover African American leaders, politics and social conditions, the Communist Party, and other topics.
Series XVI. Writings by Others, contains published and unpublished articles by U.S. Communists and progressives, and by writers from the Soviet Union.
Series XVII: Audiocassettes contains 373 recordings (Oral Histories Collection number 57). Most contain lectures and speeches, often of an educational nature, given by Jackson, usually at Communist Party forums. There are also some thirty recordings of talks by other Party leaders, including Gus Hall and Henry Winston, a recording of an event celebrating Jackson's 60th birthday, and an interview with Jackson by his daughter, Kathy. The audiocassettes are housed separately in the Library's Oral History collection as Oral Histories Collection 57.
This collection is temporarily closed to researchers.
Arrangement
The files are organized into seventeen series:
I, Biographical and Memorabilia
II, Clippings
III, Communist Party USA
IV, Correspondence
V, Correspondence, Army
VI, Freedomways (Esther Cooper Jackson)
VII, Esther Cooper Jackson Papers
VIII, Lectures
IX, Notebooks
X, Smith Act
XI, Southern Negro Youth Congress
XII, Speeches
XIII, Subject Files
XIV, Writings, Published
XV, Writings, Unpublished
XVI, Writings by Others
XVII, Audiocassettes (Oral History Collection 57)
The folders in the various series/subseries are arranged alphabetically or chronologically.
Separated Material
James E. and Esther Cooper Jackson Photographs (Photographs 221).
James E. Jackson Audiocassettes (OH 057)
Bloice, Carl; Brown, Lloyd L. (Lloyd Louis), 1913-; Burnham, Dorothy.; Burnham, Louis E.; Civil Rights Congress (U.S.).; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964; Davis, Ossie; Dee, Ruby; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961.; Dennis, Peggy; Du Bois, Shirley Graham, 1896-1977.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Duberman, Martin B.; Durr, Virginia Foster; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Freedomways Associates.; Gerson, Simon W.; Hall, Gus; Harrington, Oliver W. (Oliver Wendell), 1912-1995; Hudson, Hosea.; Hunton, Alphaeus, 1903-1970.; Jackson, Esther Cooper; Jackson, James E., 1914-2007; National Committee to Defend Negro Leadership.; National Negro Congress (U.S.).; Neruda, Pablo, 1904-1973.; Pittman, John.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Southern Negro Youth Congress.; Strong, Edward E., 1914-1957; United Tobacco Stemmers and Laborers Union. Local 279.; Walker, Alice, 1944-; Washington, Mary Helen; West, Jim; Williams, Robert F. (Robert Franklin), 1925-1996; Winston, Henry, 1911-1986.; Winter, Carl.; African American communists.; African American soldiers |v Correspondence.; African American youth |x Political activity.; African Americans |x Civil rights.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Communism |z United States; Communism.; Communist trials |z United States.; Correspondence.; Lectures.; Manuscripts (document genre); Notebooks.; Oral histories (document genres); Periodicals.; Reports.; Southern States.; Speeches.; Transcripts.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Participation, African American.
- Series I: Biographical and Memorabilia.
  - 60th Birthday Acknowledgement, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Applications (Grants, Jobs), Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Army (Letters of Recommendations, Statements, Personal Placement Questionnaires), 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Army Diary, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Author's Contracts, Royalty Statements, 1974, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Boy Scouts Clipping, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cards from the Family, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conference Tags and Other Memorabilia, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CVs and Biographies, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ID cards, 1960s, 1970s, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Daisy Petals and Shrapnel Fragments Testament and Commentary of an American Negro Soldier, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diaries, 1981, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Family History (handwritten, unknown author), Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family Letters, 1963-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Greetings for Jackson, 1954-1957, 1977, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Honorary Doctorate Diploma from Moscow University, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Jackson, Alice (Clippings, Rejection from University of Virginia, Greetings on her 80th Birthday), 1935, 1989, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jackson, Clara, 1960, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jackson, Esther Cooper: Family Record, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jackson, Esther Cooper: Honorary Degree as a Doctor of Humane Letters awarded by Long Island University, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Jackson, Harriet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jackson, James Sr., 1914, 1917, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jackson, James Sr.: Committee of Civic Improvement League, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jackson, Maurice [no relation]: James and Esther Jackson: A Personal Perspective [3 pp.], 2008 (Box 1, Folder 23A)
  - Jackson, William H. Jr., 2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Interview transcripts with James and Esther Jackson (by Erik S. McDuffie, Mary Helen Washington), Undated, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Liberal Study Group, Howard University, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Memorabilia (checks, records), Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Memorabilia (Delegate and Conference Participant Badges and Membership Cards), Undated (Box 1, Folder 27A)
  - Memorabilia, Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27B)
  - Nomination for M.A. at Goddard College, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Pharmacy, 1985-1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Prison Letters, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Retirement Speech, to the National Board, C.P.U.S.A., 1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Smithfield Court Tenants, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - University Transcripts, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Virginia Union University, Class of 1935, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - William L. Patterson Foundation - Founders' Certificate, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Writings about Jackson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Young Communist League Honors, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Cards and Invitations Received, ca. 1970-ca. 1990 (Box 1, Folder 38-38D)
- Series II: Clippings.
  - Clippings - Book reviews (of Jackson's Books), 1967, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings - Pictorial, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings by Jackson - Translated into Foreign Languages, 1961-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings by Jackson, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings by Jackson, 1980s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings about Jackson, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings about Jackson, 1930s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings about Jackson, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings about Jackson, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series III: Communist Party.
  - Amendments to National Resolution on the Afro-American Struggle, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Davis Club of Chicago on National Education Commission Report (attached: Preliminary Report on Public Education), Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Jackson's Personal Notes on Committee Meetings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Education Department / Commission, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Negro Question, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Party Statements (undated) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Statement of Aims and Policy, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Communist Party Documents, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Communist Party Documents - Workers School, 1938-1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Communist Party Documents - Vote for Victory - Defeat the Appeasers, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Communist Party Documents - on Women's Role, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Constitution of the Communist Party of the United States of America, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 17th National Convention, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 18th National Convention, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Jackson's Hand Written Notes on National Board Meeting, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The United Front -- Communist Party of Ohio, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 22nd National Convention, Main Political Resolution, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Red Letter-- Communist Party of Illinois, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Second Draft of the Party Program, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of Political Committee Meeting on African-American Politics, ca.1980s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Communist Party Documents - Program Committee, Dec 12, 1990-Dec 13, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Communist Party Documents, 1992-2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Correspondence.
  - Subseries IV:A: Chronological Correspondence.
    - Correspondence, Chronological, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, Chronological, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 22)